<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Robin Smith - Full-stack Web Developer</title>
    <description>Experienced full-stack web developer building custom web applications and integrations using the best frameworks and cloud technologies.
</description>
    <link>https://rsmith.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://rsmith.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 15:53:22 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 15:53:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.6.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Dicsaurus</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve created a small tool named &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/robinrob/dicsaurus&quot;&gt;Dicsaurus&lt;/a&gt;, out of a need to quickly look up
 words and synonyms for words, and out of a desire to make it as painless as possible. It currently works in two
 modes: dictionary and thesaurus. In programmer style I also
  wanted to be able to customise the output. Previously I was using the command-line &lt;code&gt;dict&lt;/code&gt; tool in OS X, and for
  thesaurus just opening thesaurus.com in a browser, with the search term encoded into a URL parameter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dicsaurus is just a simple python script that makes HTTP callouts to &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.oxforddictionaries.com/&quot;&gt;Oxford Dictionaries API&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/robinrob/dicsaurus/blob/master/README.md&quot;&gt;readme&lt;/a&gt; explains how to set it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Example usage in dictionary mode&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word &amp;#39;blue&amp;#39; turns out to be a good test word for both dictionary and thesaurus modes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Command: &lt;code&gt;./dicsaurus.py -t blue&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Output:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext&quot; data-lang=&quot;plaintext&quot;&gt;Results from Oxford University Press:

Definition(s) for 'blue'

   blue (Adjective)

      Example(s):
         a blue silk shirt
         the clear blue sky
         deep blue eyes
         he's feeling blue
         a blue movie
         the successful blue candidate

      Etomologie(s):
         Middle English: from Old French bleu, ultimately of Germanic origin and related to Old English blǣwen ‘blue’ and Old Norse blár ‘dark blue’ (see also blaeberry)


   blue (Noun)

      Example(s):
         she was dressed in blue
         armchairs in pastel blues and greens
         the dark blue of his eyes
         a flyweight boxing blue
         did you have a blue or what?
         his tactical blue in saying the opposition wasn't ready to govern
         only an Aussie could make a red-headed man ‘Blue.’


   blue (Verb)

      Example(s):
         blued paper
         the day would haze, the air bluing with afternoon
         the light dims, bluing the retina
         they blued the shirts and starched the uniforms

      Etomologie(s):
         mid 19th century: perhaps a variant of blow&amp;lt;/code&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/pre&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Example usage in thesaurus mode&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Command: &lt;code&gt;./dicsaurus.py -t blue&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Output:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext&quot; data-lang=&quot;plaintext&quot;&gt;Results from Oxford University Press:

Synonym(s) for 'blue'

   blue (Adjective)

      Snynoym(s):
         sky-blue
         azure
         cobalt
         cobalt blue
         sapphire
         cerulean
         navy
         navy blue
         saxe
         saxe blue
         Oxford blue
         Cambridge blue
         ultramarine
         lapis lazuli
         indigo
         aquamarine
         turquoise
         teal
         teal blue
         cyan
         of the colour of the sky
         of the colour of the sea

      Example(s):
         she had bright blue eyes

      Snynoym(s):
         depressed
         down
         sad
         saddened
         unhappy
         melancholy
         miserable
         sorrowful
         gloomy
         dejected
         downhearted
         disheartened
         despondent
         dispirited
         low
         in low spirits
         low-spirited
         heavy-hearted
         glum
         morose
         dismal
         downcast
         cast down
         tearful

      Example(s):
         Dad had died that year and Mum was feeling a bit blue

      Snynoym(s):
         indecent
         dirty
         rude
         coarse
         vulgar
         bawdy
         lewd
         racy
         risqué
         salacious
         naughty
         wicked
         improper
         unseemly
         smutty
         spicy
         raw
         off colour
         ribald
         Rabelaisian

      Example(s):
         a blue movie

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://rsmith.io/blog/dicsaurus-tool/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rsmith.io/blog/dicsaurus-tool/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Python 3.6 string interpolation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I learned about this around six months ago, and since then I&amp;#39;ve barely used it because I hadn&amp;#39;t used it enough to
remember the syntax. And since it&amp;#39;s recent, Googling for it wasn&amp;#39;t returning anything either - since I hadn&amp;#39;t realised it was
unique to versions 3.6 onwards, I wasn&amp;#39;t looking in the correct documentation versions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially Python 3.6 introduces a new form of string interpolation that is similar to the way one can embed variables
into strings in Ruby:
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;msg = &amp;quot;Hello at last!&amp;quot;
puts &amp;quot;#{msg}&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same example in Python 3.6:
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;python&quot;&gt;msg = &amp;quot;Hello at last!&amp;quot;
print(f&amp;quot;{msg}&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Output:
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; Hello at last!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which I find to be a lot nicer than:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&quot;{msg}&quot;.format(msg=msg)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most situations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://rsmith.io/blog/python-3-6-string-interpolation/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rsmith.io/blog/python-3-6-string-interpolation/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Going Freelance</title>
        <description>&lt;h2&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently gave a &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/bdfuv9c3WLM?t=2589&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; on going freelance at a &lt;a href=&quot;http://techmeetup.co.uk/&quot;&gt;TechMeetup&lt;/a&gt; event in Edinburgh.
The process of preparing for the talk really got me thinking about my experiences, and I will summarise some of the
things I spoke about here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly after I began my first full-time job as a web developer, I began hearing about freelancers through general conversation.
The comments associated with them were usually something about their high pay relative to equivalent full-time employed
workers. Sometimes a colleague would mention that
they had freelanced in the past, before returning to full-time work, which intrigued me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing I realised was that the app stores/marketplaces of the main mobile
platforms were mature and I knew there were developers out there who could make a full-time living just by producing
entirely their own applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years later, a colleague and good friend admitted that he was even making a small monthly income from the Android Market, for a couple
of apps he had made in-between finishing his PhD and starting his first job. This excited me, whilst at the same time making
myself feel somewhat underachieving! However my priority at the time was to keep building software development and
cloud technology experience, so I filed these ideas away in the back of my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years later, I found myself thinking about freelancing more and more, and eventually decided to set myself a firm target. I
chose a nice round number and decided I wanted to be freelancing by that particular age. Later, a colleague decided to make
the same jump before me, and told me all about his experiences throughout the process, and how much he was enjoying the
benefits of freelancing. Another friend in London revealed he was also contracting in a different area of work.
I chose a date in the following year by which I wanted to be freelancing, and an amount of money I&amp;#39;d
need to have in the bank by then before making the jump (enough to live for at least 6 months without work).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed to beat my age target for beginning freelancing, which is a satisfying feeling. I have now been freelancing
for two and a half years, so I thought it would be nice to write down the main pros and cons from my perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Switch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I had left my job, I began looking for work. It was an exciting period because time felt critical, and at the same
time I was enjoying the absolute freedom of the break from work. Fortunately, my freelancing software developer friend was able to refer
an enquiry to me, since my friend was busy at the time, and I ended up with a job just a few weeks later after a quick
chat in a cafe. The feeling of satisfaction at succeeding with the first job was great. And once you have reached that point
it is really up to you whether you want to continue with freelancing or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time, I found many great benefits to the freelancing lifestyle, including for me the ability to work home.
But there can be drawbacks too, although it is easy to imagine the pros
and cons being completely different for different people. If you find the cons outweigh the pros, you can always go back, so
freelancing is the sort of thing I definitely recommend trying for someone who is considering it, because at the very
least it is a great experience-building experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Benefits of freelancing (or contracting)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a subtle distinction between &amp;#39;freelancing&amp;#39; and &amp;#39;contracting&amp;#39;. But I use &amp;#39;freelancing&amp;#39; loosely - for me it means the freedom to take on contract jobs,
whilst also being responsible for your own learning and keeping up with the technology, and the potential for making
money from personal projects. So it&amp;#39;s to do with independence. These are the benefits i&amp;#39;ve experienced so far:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Independence.&lt;/strong&gt; The feeling of personal independence is extremely rewarding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pay&lt;/strong&gt;. You get more pay per hour, and as long as you can minimise the gaps between jobs, this results in higher overall
income.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Downsides of freelancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lower job security.&lt;/strong&gt; This is an obvious one, but it will have different importance to different people, depending on their
current circumstances. So you have to weight it based on personal considerations too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Responsibility&lt;/strong&gt; This can be scary to some, especially when it comes to tax. However if your income situation is complex,
you probably want an accountant anyway. If your only source of income is from freelancing jobs, then I find it to actually
be relatively simple (in the UK), despite the seemingly-complex rules. I know this is a controversial opinion!

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team integration&lt;/strong&gt; You may be seen as more of an ‘outsider’ when working in a team of full-time employed people, resulting
in weaker team relationships. Just try to be super easy to work with and helpful at all times.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More time spent on admin, marketing etc. instead of actual job&lt;/strong&gt; As a result of the higher personal responsibility,
a significant amount of your time will be spent not indulging in your passion for coding. However I always say that
everybody needs variety, in both environment and day-to-day tasks. Breaks from strenuous thinking always promote
creativity. Can you tell that I&amp;#39;m an incessant optimist?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Maybe you could just sell your own products instead?&lt;/strong&gt; If independence is what you are after, then a possibility is
to start working on personal projects whilst doing your full-time job, with the aim to monetise your products. This seems
to be like it could be a wonderful combination, giving you a stable platform to indulge in your creative urges. On the
other hand, freelancing can potentially allow you to do this &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; free up even more time to do so.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Benefits to working from home&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The ability to work in your own environment.&lt;/strong&gt; We can be more efficient when we can have our surroundings exactly
how we want them. Once you have setup your own personal office, it takes a big variable out of the equation. You
can also cook breakfast and lunch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoiding commutes.&lt;/strong&gt; Doing no commuting at all literally returns hours of the day back to you,
to use however you want. It also means that whilst everybody else in the outside world is stressfully trying to get to work on time, and back,
you have the leisure to spend that on whatever you want. If you like to enjoy hobbies in your spare time, this is a real benefit.
All the good developers have some personal project they&amp;#39;d like to spend more time on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flexibility.&lt;/strong&gt; If you are the sort of person
who naturally tends towards the most efficient ways of doing things, this can increase your efficiency a lot. Working from home
leads to being able to precisely setting your own schedule - when to start work, when to have lunch, for how long, and when to finish.
If you need to pop out to do some errand during the day, you can just find a convenient time
and go and do it. Parcels? You are always in, so these are never a problem either. I find this benefit to be priceless.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Added motivation to socialise.&lt;/strong&gt; Working from home can feel isolating at times, but you can turn it into a positive thing
by using that to motivate yourself to socialise more in ways that you may not have otherwise. When you&amp;#39;re around people in an office all day, you may not want to go
and be around even more people in the evening. But when working from home, you really relish it. So start some sociable hobbies that
you may not otherwise have done. I joined a choir, and it&amp;#39;s one of the best decisions i&amp;#39;ve made yet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Possible downsides to working from home&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Responsibility.&lt;/strong&gt; With the increase in flexibility with your time, comes a great responsibility to manage it well and be efficient. When
you can choose your working hours, you will naturally want to work when it most suits you. But it can also be tempting to
become lazy, even without realising it. Even when you see yourself as a non-lazy person! If you find yourself getting up later than you&amp;#39;d like,
and doing less hours, or working during hours in which you&amp;#39;re less productive, or working at the weekends, it&amp;#39;s important to notice and self-correct these things.
You can come out of it with much clearer goals about what you actually want to achieve, and more therefore motivation and discipline towards achieving those goals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loneliness.&lt;/strong&gt; This can take some time to have its effect, but the effect of rarely interacting with people in person during
your working day can be quite
profound. It can lead to a massive loss in productivity in all areas of your life,
and you may not even notice it for a while either. You need to recognise it and find a solution, like changing to a job
where you are working on-site, or a combination of that and working from home. Or working in coffee shops for some of the day.
The great thing is you have the freedom to do something really novel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You get sick of your home.&lt;/strong&gt; As well as sapping your motivation for work, this can even put you off doing hobbies that you would
usually do at home. The solutions are similar to the ones for loneliness above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No company benefits.&lt;/strong&gt; Such as holidays. Not having paid holiday means that whenever you are going on holiday, the true &amp;#39;cost&amp;#39; of the holiday
now includes the time you spent on holiday multiplied by your rate! When deciding your day rate, you need to take into account all
of the monetary benefits you may be missing out on by going independent. And if you are making enough, then this will not be a worry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unpredictable work load&lt;/strong&gt; This is one of those risk factors you must factor in when deciding your date rate, and you have to
judge the risk of each project or job individually. Fortunately in software development at the moment, the demand is fairly high,
so for a good developer making a consistent effort to build contacts and exposure, it is definitely possible to maintain a consistently-high
work load. You can always fill your gaps with work on personal projects. Get to be thinking like an entrepreneur.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The importance of cleanly dividing your work and leisure time I found to be fundamental. My personal choice is actually to work from 8am-4pm,
as these are the hours when I am most productive. It also keeps me in sync with the schedules of friends, with obvious benefits.
As much as we sometimes malign it, the working week is actually pretty-effectively designed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To achieve my aim of making a living by freelancing has been very gratifying. The challenge and process of doing
your own marketing and network-building I find to be great fun. There are ways in which I could have being doing these much better,
and I&amp;#39;ve recently learned a lot about this subject. I will be writing about it soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going into the future, I am completely open-minded about whether I continue freelancing or go back into a
full-time employed position. I can clearly see the advantages of either. At the moment, I am actually swaying towards
the latter. I am neither an evangelist nor detractor for freelancing - everybody can gain something out of it, and
it will be different things to different people. People also change, but the one thing that you should aim to keep constant
is your enthusiasm for your craft, and for people.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://rsmith.io/blog/going-freelance/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rsmith.io/blog/going-freelance/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Maintaining a personal code library</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;These days rapid Google searches are an invaluable tool for developers who are constantly getting to grips with a
new language, framework or technique, where reading lengthy documentation would be a waste of time when the problem
is simply a matter of finding the correct syntax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very very often I find the answer is much more valuable to me when shown in a way in which it is best understood by
myself. And there are certain things that when you are switching between languages on varying timescales, you find
yourself repeatedly needing to look up. They can often be unique to your particular style of coding - for example
it may be that you want to remind yourself of a particular pattern for implementing a decorator method in Python, or of
implementing a Class and inheritance structure in Javascript. The questions and answers are not always trivial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this reason I am very careful to record in short scripts all such useful examples and commit and push these into
source code repositories that I maintain for myself. I have structured the repositories in a way (one repository per language,
split into &lt;code&gt;practice&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;projects&lt;/code&gt; directories), that they are highly
amenable to searching by automated tool (usually ZSH function), so that usually to find the answer to a problem it is
a matter of running one command from wherever I happen to be, and I am instantly reminded of the code that I need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Holding onto your precious code is also a matter of pride in craft. Code does not often come cheap and can require
significant expenditure of your time to find good solutions. I do not want that time to go to waste by having to repeat
the process in future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://rsmith.io/blog/personal-code-library/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rsmith.io/blog/personal-code-library/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Learn Regex or Regret It</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you like challenging logic puzzles? Games that give you a set of root principles then offer up increasingly hard
problems that require ever-more creative ways of using the root principles to solve?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do, and once I actually sat down to dedicate some time to the subject of regular expressions, the
above viewpoint is the way in which I came to view this learning process. Learning how to use regular expressions is an exercise of
applying the known rules of the game to situations that require your creativity, logical thinking and intuition to solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all things that are difficult to do well, if you can make the process of mastering it into a game you will perform
much better. The task of solving regex problems is a &lt;em&gt;perfect&lt;/em&gt; candidate for game-making!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you only reach this stage in your appreciation of regular expressions then you may already find great value in them. But they
are also among one of the few truly powerful tools available to programmers that transcend programming language, framework
or project that you are working on. If you find Javascript to be a language worth learning because of its popularity
and relevance - a mere programming language, or AngularJS a framework worth learning because it&amp;#39;s popular at the
moment - then you should logically view a tool like regular expressions as being of great importance and relevance in your profession.
Regular expressions have been around for decades and have changed little in their basic philosophy and syntax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More important than any of the above great reasons for learning how to use regular expressions, the fact remains that they
are an incredibly powerful and efficient way of solving certain types of text-reading and text-manipulation problems.
To take a (simplified) example that is well-suited to the application of a regex solution: let&amp;#39;s say that you want
to read in some user input to specify the first line of an address, which must be a number followed by alphabetical
strings of characters, e.g. &amp;#39;41 Princes Street&amp;#39;. Furthermore, each alphabetical string must have its initial
character capitalised. So &amp;#39;41 123 Princes Street&amp;#39; would be invalid, as would &amp;#39;41 princes Street&amp;#39; or &amp;#39;41 Princes123 Street&amp;#39;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s first solve the problem without using a regex. You may write some code like this (for example in Python):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;python&quot;&gt;#!/usr/bin/env python

import sys

address = sys.argv[1]

parts = address.split(' ')

try:
    house_number = int(parts[0])
    street = parts[1:-1]

    for street_part in street:
        assert street_part.istitle() and street_part.isalpha()

    print 'Valid address!'

except Exception as e:
    print 'Invalid address'
    
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An equivalent script using a regex method might go like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;python&quot;&gt;#!/usr/bin/env python

import sys, re

address = sys.argv[1]

regex = re.compile('\A[0-9]+ ([A-Z][a-z]+\ ?)+\Z')
res = regex.match(address)

if hasattr(res, 'group'):
    print 'Valid address!'
    
else:
    print 'Invalid address'

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The regular expression says: match a string with the following properties:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Begins with a string of one more more digits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The initial string of digits is followed by a space character, then one or more of: (alphabetical string with capitalised initial character, optionally followed by a space character)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The string ends on the last of the occurrence of (alphabetical string with capitalised initial character, optionally followed by a space character)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this particular example with the given constraints on the format of the address I would prefer the regular expression
solution, as it expresses very concisely the conditions being imposed for validity of the input. For me it is a lot
easier to write and to read and therefore easier to get right and to not make mistakes. It also utilises a neat aspect
of regular expressions: recursive matching of a sub-expression (the alphabetical strings following the number in the address
line).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not every instance of any given type of problem is best solved using any particular tool, and this is true with regular 
expressions. A judgement must be made based on many factors and constraints on which is the best method to use to solve the problem,
where &amp;#39;best&amp;#39; is defined by a lot of factors specific to the problem and the environment and circumstances in which it is being solved.
Regular expressions are just one additional tool that you have available for consideration when making this decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason why I think that it would be regretful not to learn how to use regular expressions, is that since making the
effort to learn how to use this tool, I have personally encountered many situations where they have been a priceless tool, saving
me time and frustration, and giving a feeling of satisfaction when the correct regex for a problem is discovered! It&amp;#39;s
not often that such a simple, short string of characters can give such power.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://rsmith.io/blog/learn-regex-or-regret-it/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rsmith.io/blog/learn-regex-or-regret-it/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Faster Variable Debugging</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Almost inevitably whilst debugging code, regardless of any additional tools that you may have available (e.g.
browser development tools when debugging front-end code), it can be desirable to quickly print the contents of a
variable to the program output. Maybe you don&amp;#39;t have the time to learn how to use a more comprehensive tool in that moment,
or doing so would actually take more time. You can find yourself repetitively typing the same mundane set of characters
out that results in printing something in the language that you happen to be using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use my terminal extensively for little time-saving pieces of automation, that over the course of a day can have a big
impact on your efficiency. One example is a set of short commands for printing things out in various languages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Javascript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code&gt;js_log&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;copy_print &quot;console.log('$(upper $*)')&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code&gt;copy_print&lt;/code&gt; (ZSH function)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;zsh&quot;&gt;copy_print () {
    printf $@ | pbcopy &amp;&amp; pbpaste
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code&gt;upper&lt;/code&gt; (ZSH function)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;zsh&quot;&gt;upper () {
    print $@:u
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code&gt;js_log_object&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;console.log('myVar: ' + JSON.stringify(myVar, null, '\t'))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Python&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code&gt;python_log&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;python&quot;&gt;python_log () {
    copy_print &quot;print '$(upper $*)'&quot;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code&gt;python_log_var&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;python&quot;&gt;python_log_var () {
    copy_print &quot;print '$1: {var}'.format(var=$1)&quot;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;code&gt;python_log_object&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;python&quot;&gt;python_log_object () {
    copy_print &quot;import simplejson as simplejson; print '$1: {json}'.format(json=simplejson.dumps($1, indent=4))&quot;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You get the idea. Usage is simple, like this (after hot-keying to your terminal window and here using an alias &lt;code&gt;logpo&lt;/code&gt; for &lt;code&gt;log_python_object&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;zsh&quot;&gt;⚡ logpo my_var
import simplejson as simplejson; print 'my_var: {json}'.format(json=simplejson.dumps(my_var, indent=4))%
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above printed snippet is then in the clipboard and you can just paste it into the code where you want it, which of course
prints when run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;python&quot;&gt;my_var: {
    &quot;age&quot;: 28,
    &quot;name&quot;: &quot;Robin&quot;
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is fun in automating out repetitive actions that really bring down your day. It&amp;#39;s also a handy way to learn ZSH
and discover command-line tools.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://rsmith.io/blog/faster-variable-debugging/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rsmith.io/blog/faster-variable-debugging/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>ConsoleWriter jQuery Plugin</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 class=&quot;console-writer&quot; cw-sound=&quot;true&quot; cw-animation=&quot;true&quot;&gt;Edit Me!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to create a console-like typing effect on a heading element, with the heading firstly 
appearing character by character as if being typed in at a developer&amp;#39;s console. This sort of thing has already been done
as in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mattboldt.com/demos/typed-js/&quot;&gt;Typed.js&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://codepen.io/voronianski/pen/aicwk&quot;&gt;typeWriter.js&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/fardjad/realistic-typewriter.js&quot;&gt;realistic-typewriter.js&lt;/a&gt;. As with most ideas in the JS
world or software world, it is fair to say that this idea has been done before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main motivation for the project was to gain familiarity with using jQuery and I believe that embarking on a pet
project is the most fun and productive way to learn a new programming language or tool. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main feature that I wanted to implemented with the project was to allow the site visitor to modify the heading element by focusing it,
deleting existing characters and typing whatever they wanted into the element, complete with a blinking cursor at the end
of the line, as if they were typing on a command line. I added keyboard typing sounds to try to heighten the effect. Try it now by clicking any of
the headings within this blog article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;console-writer&quot; cw-typing-sound=&quot;true&quot;&gt;ConsoleWriter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I packaged the project up as a jQuery plugin: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/robinrob/console-writer.git&quot;&gt;ConsoleWriter&lt;/a&gt;,
designed with a focus on user-friendliness and configurability using options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project can be installed through Bower using the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;bower install console-writer&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The heading above this paragraph displays the default method of usage which requires
just adding the &lt;code&gt;console-writer&lt;/code&gt; class to the element. Reload the page again to see the typewriter effect. The &lt;code&gt;readme&lt;/code&gt;
file included in the repo describes the options and how to set them. There is also a &lt;code&gt;demo.html&lt;/code&gt; file which shows
example usages.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://rsmith.io/blog/console-writer-jquery-plugin/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rsmith.io/blog/console-writer-jquery-plugin/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Jekyll Gulp HAML SASS BrowserSync</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Whilst using Github&amp;#39;s Jekyll framework to build a static website, I noticed a lack of built-in HAML support. I am a big fan of using HAML to produce HTML. Apart from this lack of support for HAML, I enjoy using Jekyll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I was using Gulp to manage the build process, I needed a Gulp task to handle the HAML preprocessing. I initially tried using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/gulp-haml&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Gulp-Haml NPM package&lt;/span&gt;gulp-haml&lt;/a&gt; module in my HAML task, but it produced incorrect results a few times. I came across the node module &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/moneypenny/gulp-ruby-haml&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Gulp-Ruby-Haml NPM package&lt;/span&gt;gulp-ruby-haml&lt;/a&gt;, which is a wrapper on the Ruby gem &lt;a href=&quot;https://rubygems.org/gems/haml&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;HAML ruby package&lt;/span&gt;haml&lt;/a&gt;, and which gives accurate results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;HAML Processing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HAML files reside inside a &lt;code&gt;_haml&lt;/code&gt; folder which sits at the location of the resultant HTML files. For example:
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;project-root/
    index/
        _haml/
                index.haml
        index.html
    _includes/
        _haml/
            footer.haml
            head.haml
            nav.haml
        footer.html
        head.html
        nav.html
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The HAML build task is actually fairly slow compared to the CSS or Javascript processing tasks. It can take up to 10 seconds to process all of the HAML in the project. This is unacceptable when rebuilding on-the-fly while making changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To avoid slow build times, I use a separate &lt;code&gt;haml-watch&lt;/code&gt; task that watches the HAML files for changes, then only processes the files that changed. The stream is then piped into the code for compiling the HAML, which is contained in the function &lt;code&gt;hamlBuild()&lt;/code&gt;. This stream-piping step makes use of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/stream-combiner2&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Stream Combiner 2 NPM package&lt;/span&gt;stream-combiner2&lt;/a&gt;. Below is the code for both HAML tasks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;var haml = require('gulp-ruby-haml')
var combiner = require('stream-combiner2')

...

var config = {
    paths: {
        ...
        haml: {
            src: ['**/_haml/*.haml']
        },
        ...
    }
}

...

/* hamlBuild() contains the shared build logic used by haml-watch and haml-build */
function hamlBuild() {
    return combiner(
        haml(),
        rename(function (path) {
            path.dirname += '/../'
        })
    )
}

/* Watch and compile only changed HAML files to HTML.
 * haml-watch has its own task to avoid doing a full HAML build on each .haml file change, since a full HAML build
 * can be quite slow.
 */
gulp.task('haml-watch', function () {
    gulp.src(config.paths.haml.src, {read: false})
        .pipe(watch(config.paths.haml.src))
        .pipe(hamlBuild())
        .pipe(gulp.dest('./'))
})

/* Compile all HAML files to HTML. */
gulp.task('haml-build', function () {
    return gulp.src(config.paths.haml.src)
        .pipe(hamlBuild())
        .pipe(gulp.dest('./'))
})
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;section-heading&quot;&gt;Full Site Template&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst researching Jekyll, I noticed a few other people sharing their Jekyll setups as site templates. Here is my own &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/robinrob/jekyll-gulp-haml-sass-browsersync.git&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Source repository for Jekyll-Gulp-Haml-Sass-Browsersync project&lt;/span&gt;jekyll-gulp-haml-sass-browsersync&lt;/a&gt; template which includes my full &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/robinrob/jekyll-gulp-haml-sass-browsersync/blob/master/gulpfile.js&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Gulpfile for Jekyll-Gulp-Haml-Sass-Browsersync project on source repository page&lt;/span&gt;Gulpfile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://rsmith.io/blog/jekyll-gulp-haml-sass-browsersync/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rsmith.io/blog/jekyll-gulp-haml-sass-browsersync/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>RSS Reader Script</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I wanted a quick, lightweight way to browse and open articles from RSS feeds from within the terminal. I wrote a short
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/robinrob/rss-opener.git&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Source code repository for RSS Reader Script project&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for quickly opening RSS feed articles in a web browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Screenshot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/rss-opener.png&quot; alt=&quot;RSS Reader Usage Screenshot&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further details on its usage are given in the README file in the project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 May 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://rsmith.io/blog/rss-feed-reader/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://rsmith.io/blog/rss-feed-reader/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
